Prudential plc is a British
multinational life insurance and
financial services company headquartered
in London, United Kingdom. It was
founded in London in May 1848 as The
Prudential Mutual Assurance Investment
and Loan Association to provide loans to
professional and working people.
Prudential's largest division is
Prudential Corporation Asia, which has
over 13 million customers across 12
Asian markets and is a top-three
provider of life insurance in Hong Kong,
India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Singapore,
the Philippines and Vietnam. Its
Prudential UK division has around 7
million customers and is a leading
provider of life insurance and pensions
in the UK. Prudential also owns Jackson
National Life Insurance Company, which
is one of the largest life insurance
providers in the United States, and M&G
Investments, a Europe-focused asset
manager with total assets under
management of £547 billion at June 2014.
In December 2013 Prudential acquired the
Ghanaian life insurance company, Express
Life, marking its entry into the African
direct life insurance market. Prudential
subsequently rebranded the business as
Prudential Ghana. In September 2014, it
purchased Kenyan life insurer Shield
Assurance, rebranding the company as
Prudential Kenya.
Prudential has a primary listing on the
London Stock Exchange and is a
constituent of the FTSE 100 Index. It
had a market capitalisation of
approximately £41,630 million as of 4
February 2015. Prudential has secondary
listings on the Hong Kong Stock
Exchange, New York Stock Exchange and
Singapore Exchange.
History
= 1848 to 2000=
The company was founded on 30 May 1848
in Hatton Garden in London as The
Prudential Mutual Assurance Investment
and Loan Association providing loans to
professional and working people.
In 1854, the Company began selling the
relatively new concept of industrial
branch insurance policies to the working
class population for premiums as low as
one penny through agents acting as door
to door salesmen. The army of premium
collection agents was for many years
identified with the Prudential as the
"Man from the Pru".
It moved to its traditional home at
Holborn Bars in 1879 and converted to a
limited company in 1881. The building
was designed by Alfred Waterhouse, and
is built of terracotta manufactured by
Gibbs and Canning Limited of Tamworth —
two of the same driving forces behind
the Natural History Museum in London.
The Prudential Assurance Company Limited
was first listed on the London Stock
Exchange in 1924.
In 1986, Prudential acquired the
American insurer Jackson National Life.
In 1997, Prudential acquired Scottish
Amicable, a business originally founded
in 1826 in Glasgow as the West of
Scotland Life Insurance Company, for
£1.75bn.
In 1998, Prudential set up Egg, an
internet bank within the UK. The
subsidiary reached 550,000 customers
within nine months but had difficulty
achieving profitability. In June 2000 an
initial public offering of 21% was made
to allow for further growth of the
internet business but in February 2006
Prudential decided to repurchase the 21%
share of Egg. Egg was subsequently sold
to Citibank in January 2007.
In 1999, M&G, a UK fund management
company, was acquired.
In June 2000, the Company was first
listed on the New York Stock Exchange to
help focus on the US market.
= 2000 to present=
In October 2004 Prudential launched a
new subsidiary, PruHealth, a joint
venture with Discovery Holdings of South
Africa selling private medical insurance
to the UK market.
In April 2008 Prudential outsourced its
back office functions to Capita: about
3,000 jobs were transferred. This
significant outsourcing deal, worth an
estimated £722m over a 15-year contract,
built on Prudential's existing
relationship with Capita who took over
its Belfast operation in 2006 along with
approximately 450 employees in a smaller
operational restructure.
On 1 March 2010, Prudential announced
that it was in "advanced talks" to
purchase the pan-Asian life insurance
company of AIG, American International
Assurance for approximately £23 billion.
The deal later collapsed and AIA ended
up raising money in an IPO.
In December 2013, Prudential announced
the purchase of Ghana’s Express Life
Company. Express Life was subsequently
rebranded as Prudential Ghana. .In
April, Prudential launched two corporate
responsibility initiatives to support
education in Ghana: the Prudential
Scholarship Programme for more than 500
senior high school students, in
partnership with the NGO Plan Ghana; and
a scheme to support actuarial science
graduates.
In September 2014, Prudential purchased
Kenyan life insurer Shield Assurance and
rebranded it as Prudential Ghana,
further expanding the company’s presence
in Africa.
On 10 March 2015, it was announced that
the CEO, Tidjane Thiam, would leave
Prudential to become the next CEO of
Credit Suisse. On 1 May 2015, it was
announced that Mike Wells, head of the
company's US business, would succeed
Tidjane Thiam as CEO, on a pay package
worth up to £7.5 million.
Operations
The Company has four business units:
Prudential UK, Europe & Africa: the
business offers pensions, annuities,
savings and investments. They are
particularly well known for the sale of
with-profit bonds and pensions,
corporate pension schemes, bulk
annuities and individual annuities. The
company left the general insurance
market in 2002, licensing Churchill
Insurance to use the Prudential name.
M&G: the business offers investment
management services including retail
fund management, institutional fixed
income, pooled life, pension funds,
property and private finance. Part of
M&G, Prudential Property Investment
Managers specialises in the management
of Prudential's property assets.
Prudential Corporation Asia: based in
Hong Kong, the business is the largest
UK life assurer in Asia. It has had a
presence in the continent since 1923
when an overseas agency for life
assurance was created in India. Although
this was subsequently nationalised,
Prudential relaunched in India in 2000
as ICICI Prudential, a 26% joint venture
with ICICI Bank. As CITIC Prudential
Life, a 50–50 joint venture, they were
the first UK company to re-establish
life business in China in 2000. There
are also businesses in Hong Kong,
Taiwan, Japan, South Korea, Singapore,
Malaysia, Philippines, Thailand, Vietnam
and Indonesia. On 15 November 2011,
Prudential Corporation Asia announced
its intention to change the name of its
asset management business to Eastspring
Investments.
Jackson National Life Insurance Company:
based in Michigan, United States, the
business was purchased in 1986. It was
named after Andrew Jackson, the seventh
President of the United States of
America and started business in 1961.
Prudential RideLondon
Prudential RideLondon is an annual
two-day cycling festival that started in
2013. The third edition will take place
on Saturday 1 August and Sunday 2 August
2015.
The event was developed by the Mayor of
London and his agencies and is organised
by the London & Surrey Cycling
Partnership.. The main events are
a100-mile professional road race through
Surrey and London, and an amateur race
along the same route. Participants in
the amateur race typically raise money
for good causes. The 20,709 finishers in
the 2014 event raised more than £10
million for charity.
Swansea Bay Tidal Lagoon
In October 2014, Prudential announced
that it will invest up to £100 million
in the Swansea Bay Tidal Lagoon Power
station, a world-leading infrastructure
project. Prudential has committed to
invest £25 billion in UK infrastructure
projects over five years. Prudential
will be one of the main investors in the
scheme designed to harness tidal-energy,
which could power 120,000 homes for 120
years.
If approved, the project would take two
years to build and would create 1,850
construction jobs.
Senior management
There are currently 16 people on the
board of directors. Key individuals are:
See also
Invest Financial Corporation
Richard Woolnough
References
External links
Prudential plc web site
Yahoo! – Prudential plc Company Profile